A Guide to the Shenandoah Miscellaneous Ledgers, Minute Books and Registers, 1804-1933, bulk 1820s-1890s
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Shenandoah Miscellaneous Ledgers, Minute Books and Registers, 1804-1933
Special Collections, James Madison University
2005
41 ledgers; 6 Hollinger boxes, 2.5 oversize manuscript boxes, and 1 flat item; 4.6 linear feet
The Shenandoah Valley Miscellaneous Ledgers, Minute Books and Registers Collection, 1804-1933, is comprised of an assortment of bound record books from various organizations and individuals, documenting a variety of agricultural, social, commercial, and educational endeavors in Harrisonburg and surrounding counties in the 19th and 20th centuries.
Various Shenandoah Valley businesses and individuals
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
The collection was place on deposit by contract with the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society. The first five books were acquired in 1985; further additions were made in 1992 and 1995.
Alternative Form Available
Other Formats Available: Also available on microfilm, housed in Special Collections. Additional copies of the microfilm are owned by the Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society and the Library of Virginia.
Provenance
This collection is an amalgamation of a number of business and personal ledgers, minute books, and registers that are owned by the Historical Society. The collection is representative of multiple donations to the Historical Society, and in turn, multiple deposits to JMU.
Historical Information
Representative of books 1-5, and 20-21
Book 1 is the contract book of the Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association (now called the Tri-State Tobacco Growers Association). The Association was founded in 1922 and acts as a marketing association for the two Carolinas and Virginia, including Rockingham County where attempts were made to grow tobacco in the 1920s. Book 2, an unidentified business ledger, 1856 to 1858, lists sales of brandy as well as other items and labor. Book 3 is representative of the Grottoes Investment Company, a real estate investment company founded in 1891 at Shendun (now known as Grottoes, Virginia). The Ashby Memorial Association was a Confederate veteran's organization founded in 1897 whose membership included those from the S.B. Gibbons Camp, the Turner Ashby Chapter of the Daughters of the Confederacy and the Turner Ashby Camp of Sons of Confederate Veterans. Book 4 includes the minutes of the Ashby Memorial Association from July 1897 to April 1898. Book 5 is the school register for Public White School No. Six. The school was one of several schools located in the Plains District of Rockingham County. Book 20 records the accounts of the Valley Turnpike Company. Incorporated in 1834, the company was one of several companies authorized to construct a number of toll roads, including the one from Staunton to Winchester. Book 21 has been transcribed and published as the Michael Baker Store Account Book; see Related Material.
Scope and Content
The Shenandoah Valley Miscellaneous Ledgers, Minute Books and Registers Collection, 1804-1933, is comprised of an assortment of bound record books from various organizations and individuals, documenting a variety of agricultural, social, commercial, and educational endeavors in Harrisonburg and surrounding counties in the 19th and 20th centuries. Books 1-5 represent the first acquisition of the collection.
Arrangement
The collection was numerically arranged based on the order of accession. In the summer of 2008, the physical order of the books was changed to maximize storage space, however original numbering was retained. See the contents list below for the current physical arrangement.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
See also Kyger, M. Ellsworth. Michael Baker Store Account Book: Brocks Gap, Rockingham County, Virginia (1804-1825). Dayton, Va.: Harrisonburg-Rockingham Historical Society, 1993.
Contents List (Book:Box)
- Tobacco Growers Cooperative Association, Contract Book 1923-1924 (1:1)
  Contains marketing and association agreements. Folder contains agreement, affidavit, and two letters.
- Unidentified Business Ledger 1856-1858 (2:1)
  Lists sales of brandy as well as other items and labor.
- Grottoes Investment Company, Board of Directors Minutes April 1891-October 1892 (3:1)
- Ashby Memorial Association, Minutes July 1897-April 1898 (4:1)
- Public White School No. 6, Plains District, Rockingham County, School Register October 1888-April 1895 (5:1)
  Lists pupils, subjects, attendance registers, and description of school house.
- John Werner Ledger 1868-1876 (6:1)
  Mostly shoe repairs and manufacture.
- Unidentified Ledger 1873-1890 (7:1)
  Shoes, farm items, and labor.
- James Bush Ledger 1858-1867 (8:2)
  Records agricultural labor and payment.
- George Kiser, Estate Accounts 1895-1896 (9:2)
- David Kyle Ledger 1816-1857 (10:2)
  Includes livestock and other agricultural transactions.
- Harvey Kyle Ledger 1837-1881 (11:2)
  Lists visits and medicine, including to Negroes, and later entries concern land, bonds, etc.
- James Kyle, Account Book 1840-1846 (12:2)
  Lists various items from spices to furniture; back cover gives data on Kyle's moves around the Valley.
- David Kyle, Estate Accounts 1844-1868 (13:2)
- John Burkholder Ledger 1862-1863 (14:2)
- Funkhauser and Paul Ledger 1861-1865 (15:2)
- Unidentified Ledger, may be the Daybook of a Harrisonburg general store 1819-1820 (16:3)
- William Bushnell Ledger; Carriage Maker, Harrisonburg, VA 1818-1826 (17:3)
- Peter Roller Ledger 1833-1851 (18:3)
  Ledger of agricultural and some dry goods.
- Robert Gray Ledger 1813-1836 (19:3)
- Ledger of Valley Turnpike Company 1886-1900 (20:3)
  Accounts, bonds, interest, repairs, expenses, and salaries.
- Joseph and John Baker Daybook 1804-1821 (21:4)
  See related material for published transcription.
- David Steele Daybook 1843-1846 (22:4)
  Mostly food and wood.
- Giles Devier, Newspaper Subscription Ledger 1879-1883 (23:4)
- Post Office Account Ledger 1889-1911 (24:4)
- Cosby Mills Ledger 1893-1894, 1930 (25:5)
- Harrisonburg (Va) Post Office, Custodian's Record Book 1912-1933 (26:5)
- John C. Morrison Account Book 1857-1866 (27:5)
- Unidentified, Account Book and Travel Diary 1818-1827 (28:5)
  Partly in German.
- Singers Glen Council Minutes 1894-1919 (29:5)
- Books designated flat by "FL" were rearranged in the summer of 2008 to maximize storage space. Books FL#1-12 are listed below according to their physical arrangement.
- Addison Munch Daybook 1876-1877 (FL 6:6)
  Seven Fountains, Va.
- Seven Fountains Nursery, Apple Book 1880 (FL 8:6)
  Pictures of popular apple types.
- Bradley Foundry Ledger 1856-1871 (FL 9:6)
- Samuel Bowman Ledger 1818-1857 (FL 1:7 (oversize))
  Sales, hauling, and odd jobs; receipts and orders associated with Bowman Mill.
- James C. Bowman Ledger 1831-1832 (FL 2:7 (oversize))
  Bowman's Mill miscellaneous sales.
- Addison Munch Ledger 1866-1868 (FL 4:7 (oversize))
  Sales at the store of James Habron.
- Addison Munch Daybook 1875 (FL 5:8 (oversize))
- Addison Munch Daybook 1880-1881 (FL 7:8 (oversize))
  Seal of Addison Munch Dealer in Dry-Goods, Seven Fountains, Va, on the last page.
- Unidentified Daybook 1852-1907 (FL 10:8 (oversize))
  Tobacco, grain, etc.; McGaheysville.
- Unidentified Account Book 1885 (FL 11:9 (oversize))
  Miscellaneous.
- Unidentified Account Book 1856-1857 (FL 12:9 (oversize))
  Miscellaneous items; Lacey Spring.
- Rawley Springs Guest Register 1889-1892 (FL 3:Flat)